A Guide to the Records of Project Concern, Inc., 1969-1982
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Records of Project Concern, Inc. 1969-1982
Special Collections, James Madison University
4011
9 Hollinger boxes, 3.75 linear feet
The Records of Project Concern, Inc., 1969-1982, consist of documents pertaining to the organization's activities within Rockingham County. The documents include the organization's records, their relationships with other organizations and their programs and projects, including their annual summer camp.
Administrative personnel of Project Concern, Inc.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Greg Verson, retired JMU professor of Sociology.
Historical Information
While visiting the homes of truant children to investigate their absence in school, John Honeycutt, a visiting teacher for the Harrisonburg schools, discovered much more deeply rooted reasons for their non-attendence. It was not simply that mothers were not waking their children on time, but rather Honeycutt found families in which children did not have proper shoes, clothing, or coats to leave the house. Honeycutt initially brought this information to his church's Sunday school. His activism resulted in the organization of Project Concern, Inc., which was formally incorporated in January 1969. Its purpose was to assist with projects for the needy of Harrisonburg and Rockingham County. Project Concern worked in tandem with other local groups to satisfy needs in the community, including Social Services, the Salvation Army, Eastern Mennonite College, James Madison University, and local churches. Reflective of a national movement to combat poverty, specifically among children, Project Concern, Inc., provided basic needs for families and enriching experiences for children. Unfortunately, by the early 1980s, Project Concern's funding had vastly diminished, likely due to a national economic crisis, whereby faithful donors no longer had the means to contribute financially. In 1982 the Board of Directors of Project Concern made the decision to close their doors.
Scope and Content
The Records of Project Concern, Inc., 1969-1982, is comprised of nine Hollinger boxes, approximately 3.75 linear feet of material. The collection represents the actions and activities of a local social work organization within the communities of Harrisonburg and Rockingham County. The collection is topically arranged in eight series: Administrative Information, Financial Documents, Members, Other Agencies, Programs and Projects, Summer Camp, Miscellany and Media.
Series I, Administrative Information, consists of twenty folders of material related to the administrative operation of Project Concern. Of particular interest are the History, Bylaws and Articles of Incorporations folder and five folders of Secretary's Minutes and Records. Also included in this series are client profiles, which identify needs of particular individuals and families and Project Concern's actions on their behalf, Project Concern newsletters, and news clippings and press releases highlighting Project Concern events and accomplishments.
Series II, Financial Documents, primarily consists of eighteen folders, the majority of which are receipt books from 1970-1981, with some gaps. This series also includes financial reports, donor correspondence, and a representative sample of receipts from local businesses, 1972-1981.
Series III, Members, consists of three folders of applications for membership from individuals, organizations and volunteers. Membership involved a small financial donation and/or volunteer service.
Series IV, Other Agencies, consists of seven folders, each of which represents a local, state or national organization with which Project Concern consulted to sustain their non-profit status. In addition, Project Concern worked with Madison College (James Madison University) and Eastern Mennonite College (Eastern Mennonite University) faculty and students to facilitate programs such as Saturday Adoption, which is highlighted in the following series.
Series V, Programs and Projects, consists of ten folders containing documentation about the different programs and projects Project Concern facilitated, organized or participated in. Some of the programs figuring most prominently are the Annual Christmas Party, the Clothing and Furniture Room, and Saturday Adoption. These programs brought members of the community together to help others in the community in need.
Series VI, Summer Camp, comprises the bulk of the collection. Consisting of forty folders of materials, this series contains documents and supporting materials relating to the USDA Summer Feeding Program, as well as documentation regarding counselor and participant applications, staff training resources, and various reports and evaluations. The series is topically arranged, then chronologically where applicable.
Series VII, Miscellany, consists of two folders: drug abuse awareness, which contains c.1970s pamphlets regarding various forms of drugs; and drug treatment resources, prepared by the Commonwealth of Virginia's Division of Drug Abuse Control in 1975, which provides brief overviews of facilities throughout Virginia that provided various levels of drug treatment.
Series VIII, Media, consists of 353 color slides, and 383 photographs (most in color). Most are undated, although one folder of negatives and contact sheets for 1974 was identified. A cassette created to accompany slide presentations, a cassette titled "Lyndale S.S. class 5th and 6th grade, May 1975," and a reel-to-reel recording containing a public service announcement are housed separately.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 8 series
I. Administrative Information
II. Financial Documents
III. Members
IV. Other Agencies
V. Programs and Projects
VI. Summer Camp
VII. Miscellany
VIII. Media
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Material
Bank Statements, bills, insurance statements, and most receipts were discarded. A representative sample of receipts was maintained to document local businesses.
Contents List (Box:Folder)
- Administrative Information
  - History, Bylaws, and Articles of Incorporation (1:1)
  - Annual Meeting/Reports (1:2)
  - Board of Directors (1:3)
  - Comprehensive Employment Training Act (CETA) Information (1:4)
  - Client Profiles/Documents
    - Part 1 (1:5)
    - Part 2 (1:6)
    - Part 3 (1:7)
    - Part 4 (1:8)
  - Executive Committee (1:9)
  - Executive Director (1:10)
  - Miscellaneous Planning Documents (1:11)
  - National Council on Voluntary Action (NCVA)
    - Publications (1:12)
    - Organizational Profiles (1:13)
  - Newsletters (2:1)
  - News Clippings/Press Releases (2:2)
  - Secretary's Minutes and Recordings
    - Charter, Bylaws, and Initial Meeting Minutes (2:3)
    - Minutes, 1969-1981
      - Part 1 (2:4)
      - Part 2 (2:5)
    - Public/Group Meetings (2:6)
    - Miscellaneous (2:7)
- Financial Documents
  - Financial Statements (2:8)
  - Correspondence
    - Part 1 (2:9)
    - Part 2 (2:10)
  - Sample of Receipts (2:11)
  - Receipt Books
    - September 5, 1970 - September 15, 1971 (2:12)
    - September 20, 1971 - December 30, 1972 (2:13)
    - December 30, 1972 - August 14, 1974 (3:1)
    - August 14, 1974 - May 14, 1976 (3:2)
    - May 28, 1976 - July 27, 1977 (3:3)
    - July 18, 1977 - December 15, 1978 (3:4)
    - February 17, 1977 - April 23, 1979 (3:5)
    - December 22, 1978 - August 5, 1970 (3:6)
    - September 8, 1980 - May 11, 1981 (3:7)
    - July 5, 1973 - February 17, 1977 (3:8)
    - 1979 - 1981 (3:9)
  - Records of Accounts, 1971 (3:10)
  - Records of Receipts 1972-1982 (3:11)
  - Miscellaneous (3:12)
- Members
  - General Members (4:1)
  - Organizational Members (4:2)
  - Volunteers (4:3)
- Other Agencies
  - Commonwealth of Virgnia Resources (4:4)
  - Community Service Newsletters (4:5)
  - Local(Rockingham County)and James Madison University (4:6)
  - U.S. Federal Resources (4:7)
  - United Methodist Council on Ministries (4:8)
  - United Way (4:9)
  - Virginia Council on Social Welfare (4:10)
- Programs and Projects
  - Annual Christmas Party, 1974-1982, n.d. (5:1)
  - Big Brothers/Sisters (5:2)
  - Clothing Room (5:3)
  - Food Stamp/Bank Program (5:4)
  - Furniture Room (5:5)
  - Harris Gardens (5:6)
  - Moms and Tots (5:7)
  - Saturday Adoption, Family-to-Family, Adopt a Grandparent (5:8)
  - Standing Committees (5:9)
  - Student Projects, James Madison University (5:10)
- Summer Camp
  - Food
    - Nutritional Handbooks and Information (5:11)
    - USDA Summer Feeding Program
      - Planning Documents (5:12)
      - Regulations (5:13)
      - General
        - 1977 (5:14)
        - 1978 (5:15)
        - 1979 (6:1)
        - 1980
          - Part 1 (6:2)
          - Part 2 (6:3)
  - General
    - Attendence Records (6:4)
    - Counselor Resources (6:5)
    - Counselor Orientation (6:6)
    - Documentation
      - 1970 (6:7)
      - 1971 (6:8)
      - 1972 (6:9)
      - 1973 (6:10)
      - 1974
        - Part 1 (7:1)
        - Part 2 (7:2)
      - 1975
        - Part 1 (7:3)
        - Part 2 (7:4)
      - 1976
        - Part 1 (Manual) (7:5)
        - Part 2 (7:6)
      - 1977 (7:7)
      - 1978
        - Part 1 (7:8)
        - Part 2 (7:9)
      - 1979 (7:10)
      - 1980 (8:1)
      - 1981
        - Part 1 (8:2)
        - Part 2 (8:3)
      - 1982
        - Part 1 (8:4)
        - Part 2 (8:5)
- Miscellany
  - Drug Abuse Awareness Publications (8:6)
  - Drug Treatment Referral Guide (8:7)
  - Official Seal of Project Concern (Unfoldered)
- Media
  - Slides
    - Sheets 1-10 (9:1)
    - Sheets 11-18 (9:2)
  - Photographs
    - Part 1 (9:3)
    - Part 2 (9:4)
    - Part 3 (9:5)
  - Negatives, n.d. (9:6)
  - Negatives and Contact Sheets from 1974 (9:7)
  - Audio Cassettes and reel-to-reel Public Service Announcement (Media Cabinet)